Have you ever wondered
if there’s a natural way
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It may come as no
surprise that what we eat
directly affects our chances
of getting skin cancer.
In our first story, we look
at the best supplement
for preventing skin cancer.
Nicotinamide,
also known as niacinamide,
is a form of vitamin B3
that has been used topically
for decades
in the cosmetic field
to prevent skin aging.
So, researchers decided
to put it to the test orally
for skin cancer prevention.
In a petri dish,
skin samples taken
from breast reduction
and tummy tuck surgeries
exposed to UV
with or without niacinamide
found that it enhanced
DNA repair.
Would this translate out
into less cancer?
In a Phase II trial,
dozens of individuals
with four or more
precancerous actinic keratoses
each were randomized
to take a placebo
or 500 mg of niacinamide
once or twice a day.
Within two months,
there was a 35 percent reduction
in actinic keratoses
in the twice-a-day group,
and a 15 percent reduction
in the once-a-day group
compared to placebo.
It's not that they developed
fewer in those months,
but more
spontaneously disappeared
in the niacinamide groups.
What about actual cancers?
By month four, there were
five times fewer cancers
(11 placebo participants
developed 20 new skin cancers
versus only two
niacinamide participants
developing a total
of four new cancers).
Normally, it would be difficult
to fund studies
on nonpatentable products that
only cost a few cents a day,
but the results of this
and a similar study
on organ transplant patients
were so extraordinary
ONTRAC was born.
Oral Nicotinamide
to Reduce Actinic Cancer
was a publicly-funded
phase III trial
randomizing hundreds of people
with a personal history
of skin cancers
(actinic means UV-induced)
to 500 mg of nicotinamide
twice daily
or placebo for a full year.
By the end, there were
25 percent fewer cancers
with no significant
side effects
for just pennies a day.
You have to keep it up, though.
At a six-month follow-up
after the study was over,
the cancer rates equalized back
to baseline rates.
What are the downsides?
A study of 500 people
put on up to three grams
of niacinamide a day
for five years (trying
to prevent type 1 diabetes)
unearthed no adverse effects
over placebo
(though it failed to prevent
type 1 diabetes).
The high tolerance
of niacinamide
is partly due
to its water-soluble nature,
such that you just pee out
any excess.
But those with end-stage
kidney failure on dialysis
don't have functioning kidneys,
and so, blood levels
should be monitored,
as, in that context,
niacinamide can cause
a serious, though reversible,
drop in platelets,
which are important
for blood clotting.
High enough doses may become
toxic to the liver, though,
even with normal kidneys.
Vasodilatory side effects,
like facial flushing,
attributed to niacinamide
in some older studies
were likely due
to a less purified form
contaminated with
residual niacin.
(I know it's confusing!
Niacin, also known
as nicotinic acid,
is the precursor of,
but very different from,
niacinamide, which is
synonymous with nicotinamide.)
One concern
regarding any treatment
for a largely lifestyle disease
is that individuals may neglect
other defensive measures,
overconfident in
the supplement's protection.
Regarding drug interactions,
a concern has been raised
about taking niacinamide
together with carbamazepine,
a popular anti-seizure drug
(sold as Tegretol).
But, in general,
as the ONTRAC researchers
concluded,
"Oral nicotinamide
is safe and effective
in reducing the rates
of new nonmelanoma skin cancers
and precancerous growths
in high-risk patients."
To their credit, a 2021 survey
of skin cancer surgeons found
that three-quarters
recommended its use.
Other than nicotinamide,
how else might we protect
against skin cancer
from the inside out?
That's what I'll cover next.
Millions of skin cancers
are diagnosed every year,
the most common cancer
in the United States.
I've covered the single
most important thing we can do-
protect against exposure
to UV radiation.
What about dietary protection?
The first study to elucidate
the effect of diet
on UV-induced tumors
found that high-fat diets
accelerated tumor formation
in mice.
Within six months of UV,
fifty percent of the high-fat
fed mice had tumors
compared to only 16
in the control-fed group.
Encouragingly,
switching the mice
to a low-fat diet
after the exposure
was able to negate the tumor
exacerbating high-fat effects.
In people, a dietary pattern
characterized by meat
and fat consumption
was associated
with up to a near quadrupling
of squamous cell
carcinoma risk,
the second most common type
of skin cancer,
whereas a vegetable
and fruit pattern
was associated
with a halving of risk
(apparently driven largely
by the intake of greens).
All we needed now
was to randomize people
to low-fat diets
and see if cancer
could be prevented
in people too,
and, thanks to National
Cancer Institute funding
and a Veteran Affairs
research team,
the striking results
were published
in the New England
Journal of Medicine.
Seventy-six patients
with a history of skin cancer
(and, therefore, at high risk
of developing more)
were randomized to continue
to eat their regular diets
or switch to a quote-unquote
"low-fat" diet
of 20 percent of calories
from fat.
I put low-fat in quotes
because that's actually
a high-fat diet
compared to what's normal
for our species.
For millions of years,
our ancestors may have evolved
getting approximately
10 percent
of our calories from fat.
For millions of years,
about 99.8 percent
of our time on Earth,
it was virtually impossible
for us to consume regularly
more than 10 to 15 percent
of calories as fat.
So, that's a normal fat diet
for the human species.
A low-fat diet
would be less than that.
Though 20 percent is certainly
comparatively low fat
compared to the current
adult average
in the United States
of 37 percent.
Would a drop down to 20
make a difference?
Researchers tracked
the appearance
of actinic keratoses,
rough scaly patches
that are premalignant lesions
that turn into skin cancer,
over the next two years.
The average patient
in the control group
developed 10 lesions
in those two years,
compared to just three
in the lower-fat group.
Okay, but what about
actual skin cancers?
The results were so exciting
the same team of researchers
randomized
hundreds
of skin cancer patients
to the same two diets.
By the end of the study,
the skin cancer rate
was 10 times lower
in the lower-fat group.
Now this is no clarion call
for SnackWell's cookies.
Although fat appears
twice as bad,
high-refined carb consumption
was also found to be
significantly associated
with skin wrinkling and atrophy
among a nationwide
cross-section
of middle-aged women.
Those who consistently have
higher than normal
fasting blood sugars
are perceived to be
nearly a half year older
than they really are
for every 18 points higher
their average blood sugars are.
So, those with a prediabetic
fasting blood sugar
of like 120 milligrams
per deciliter
look about a year older
than those regularly having
a normal fasting blood sugar
of around 75.
Now, the Women's Health
Initiative randomized
nearly 50,000
postmenopausal women
to a recommendation
to eat the same lower-fat diet;
yet, there was no change
in the incidence
of skin cancer.
This is not surprising
given the poor adherence.
Only 31 percent of the women
in the intervention group
complied with
the dietary recommendations.
It turns out healthy diets
may only work
if you actually eat them.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.